https://www.financialexpress.com/opinion/need-a-unified-digital-policy-framework/2092001/

Unified digital policy framework is a need of the hourBy: Deepak Maheshwari | September 26, 2020 5:15 AMSuch an overarching framework can be the skeleton for all state and central policies on the various areas that concern, or are impacted by, digital technology—from AI, cybersecurity and data privacy to healthtech, fintech, etcIn between, there was National Digital Communication Policy, 2018 and comments were sought on the Draft PDP Bill as drafted by the committee chaired by Justice Srikrishna.Hardly a month passes by without a new policy proposal touching the digital ecosystem. Moreover, these are no longer restricted to just telecom, information technology and broadcasting, but often impact financial services, healthcare, education, agriculture and more.A spate of policy proposalsThis frenzy is to be expected, given our increasing dependence on the digital ecosystem of hyper-connected persons, entities and things.Related NewsRenewable Energy Generation: Betting on the green power marketDelivery Wise: Universal national social profile will help cut inclusion-exclusion errors & improve efficiencyA quantum leap: DRDO’s quantum-comm success big, now focus on NM-QTAIn September, NITI Aayog sought comments on the Data Empowerment and Protection Architecture (DEPA). The Independence Day address of the prime minister mentioned the upcoming National Cyber Security Strategy, extending optical fibre to six lakh villages; and, the National Digital Health Mission (NDHM). A few days later, the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Trai) published yet another consultation paper on broadband. In July, the ministry of electronics & IT (MeitY) had published a report on the Non-Personal Data (NPD), followed by NITI Aayog seeking comments on the Draft Framework for Responsible AI.Last December, the Personal Data Protection Bill, 2019 (PDP Bill) was introduced in Parliament and referred to a joint committee. Incidentally, Section 91 therein deals with NPD even as the same ministry had already set up a committee of experts on NPD. In November, the office of the National Cyber Security Coordinator had sought inputs on the National Cyber Security Strategy. Draft reports on various aspects of AI by four committees under the auspices of MeitY had also been published, and yes, in February 2019, there was the Draft National Policy on E-Commerce.A draft amendment of the intermediary guidelines was published in December 2018, and in June that year, NITI Aayog had published a discussion draft on the National Strategy for Artificial Intelligence. In between, there was National Digital Communication Policy, 2018 and comments were sought on the Draft PDP Bill as drawn up by the committee chaired by Justice BN Srikrishna.Same-same, but differentBasically, there is a set of interconnected issues crying for policy attention: Digital access and inclusion, AI, cybersecurity, personal and non-personal data, intermediary liability, and, blockchain. In addition, diplomacy is engaged in developing cyber norms under the aegis of the UN and, internet governance at multi-stakeholder platforms. Then there is e-commerce, healthtech, fintech, etc.Even well-resourced think tanks and seasoned policy professionals find it difficult to keep track of these similar yet different efforts. However, beyond sheer volume, variety and velocity lies the challenge of volubility with hardly any agency providing a sneak peek into what is coming through the pipe.Policy patchworkWhile telecom remains unambiguously a central subject, it seems that IT and allied domains are becoming de facto concurrent subjects, well almost! After all, every state has an IT policy, and some even have one for AI, cybersecurity and even data protection.Unsurprisingly, there are numerous gaps and overlaps in such a patchwork of policies, legislation and regulatory proposals. For example, Section 91 in the Personal Data Protection Bill, 2019 deals with the ‘non-personal data’ (NPD). Likewise, the Draft E-Commerce Policy delves more with data than commerce.This is more than anybody can chew, and the sheer capacity constraints across government and outside only amplifies the challenge. After all, policymaking is too important to be left to the policymakers alone.New apparatus, new architectureIn a quasi-federal democracy like ours, public policy is no child’s play, amidst all the chaos. But the situation is ripe for a new apparatus and a new architecture of policymaking in general and for the digital space in particular.Firstly, the PMO must enunciate an overarching and oversee a ‘Unified Digital Policy Framework’ (UDPF) framework. Outlining a vision, basic principles and establishing institutional mechanism, UDPF would be the pole star guiding all allied policies such as AI, cybersecurity and data privacy as well as those in the realms like education, healthcare and fintech.Secondly, the process must be inclusive, lawful, transparent, responsive, accountable and evidence-based. Public consultation is an opportunity for value addition, not an inconvenience.Thirdly, it must be accompanied by a robust Regulatory Impact Assessment (RIA) detailing the rationale for particular choices as well as safeguards against unintended yet foreseeable consequences.Last but not least, we need an institutional mechanism for implementation, periodic reviews, including qualitative and quantitative triggers.The author is Public policy consultant and senior visiting fellow, ICRIER. Views are personal
Get live Stock Prices from BSE, NSE, US Market and latest NAV, portfolio of Mutual Funds, calculate your tax by Income Tax Calculator, know market’s Top Gainers, Top Losers & Best Equity Funds. Like us on Facebook and follow us on Twitter.Financial Express is now on Telegram. Click here to join our channel and stay updated with the latest Biz news and updates.HomeOPINIONUnified digital policy framework is a need of the&nbsphourAdvertisement Stock MarketMost ReadTravelling on side lower berth to get comfortable: Indian Railways introduces innovative design; Watch videoStaff Selection Commission Recruitment 2020: Application process ends soon for 4,726 posts — check detailsAre Aliens for real? Ex-Israeli Space Chief makes big claim, says Trump is aware tooShare Market Highlights: Sensex snaps gaining spree, ends 143 pts lower, Nifty closes at 13,478; IRCTC tanks 11%Income Tax Return: Problems in ITR excel utilities mar date extension reliefAmid high inflation and low FD rates, for what duration should you invest in fixed deposits?Burger King India IPO: Here’s how to check share allotment status via registrar, BSE website Two stocks to buy for near term gains while Nifty trades in overbought territoryFarm Laws: Centre must not yield to ‘mandatory MSP’ demand & refrain from imposing levies on non-APMC salesWalmart plans to increase exports from India to $10 billion by 2027AdvertisementTop NewsUPL share price jumps 4%; management clarifies on whistleblower claims, denies allegationsMarket LIVE: Sensex hits fresh record high, jumps 200 pts, Nifty above 13,500; ONGC surges 8%, IRCON up 9%How to regain control of your finances after festive overspendingFarmers Protest Live News: Who will blink first? Farmers stick to rollback demand despite fresh outreach by CentreMeet astronaut Raja, only Indian-American to be part of NASA's manned Moon mission ArtemisIndia's COVID-19 caseload rises to 97.96 lakh with 29,398 fresh infectionsAsian shares boosted by coronavirus vaccines hopes, Brexit deadline casts shadowChina to step up fiscal support for new economic strategyIn pandemic-hit 2020, world records biggest ever drop in carbon dioxide emissionsStocks in focus: IRCTC, TCS, HCL Tech, TVS Motor, Muthoot Finance, Mahindra & Mahindra, UPLAdvertisementSwitch to Hindi EditionHomeMarkets MarketsCafeinvestCommoditiesIpo NewsStocksEconomyTechAutoIndustryIndustryBanking & FinanceTechnologySME/Start-upsJobsEducationMutual FundsMoneyMoneyInsuranceIncome TaxInfrastructureInfrastructureRailwaysAviationRoadwaysIndiaUS StocksINVESTSportsLifestyleLifestyleTravel & TourismHealthScienceFrom The PrintInternationalEdits & ColumnsOpinionFE 360PoliticsEconomyPersonal FinanceFront PageFE InsightFE@campusBrand WagonToday’s PaperePaperPhotosVideosHoroscopeArchiveNewsCompanies, Stock QuotesNext Stories1Renewable Energy Generation: Betting on the green power market2Delivery Wise: Universal national social profile will help cut inclusion-exclusion errors & improve efficiency3A quantum leap: DRDO’s quantum-comm success big, now focus on NM-QTA
